Guide to the Rugh Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Rugh Family Papers
1921-2000
1930-1952
RG 244
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(4 boxes)
Correspondence and writings document the life and work of Dwight Rugh, his wife Winifred and their daughter Betty Jean during their service in China 1930-1951. The Rughs taught and did administrative work for the Yale-in-China Association at Yali Middle School, in Hunan Province. Winifred also taught at Shanghai American School, where Betty Jean attended for several years. Dwight Rugh was the last representative of the Yale-China Association to leave China in 1951, his application for an exit permit having been delayed for several months.
Rugh, D. DeK. (Dwight DeKalb)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Betty Rugh Elder
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1899 Sep Dwight Dekalb Rugh (DR) born in Clarion, Pennsylvania where his parents were teachers in Clarion Normal School
ca. 1902 DR moved to California where his father was a school principal and later a professor of education a the University of California at Berkeley. The Rugh family, including DR's brother Charles and sister Winifred, lived in Los Gatos, CA where DR met his future wife, also named Winifred. She was the daughter of the town's Presbyterian minister.
1921 DR received B.A. from University of California and went to Hawaii, where he started the student YMCA at the University of Hawaii. Winifred attended normal school and taught Kindergarten in California.
1924 DR returned to California to marry Winifred (WR) and together they returned to Hawaii for three more years.
1927-1930 DR and WR moved to New Haven where he attended and graduated from Yale Divinity School.
1930 DR and WR were invited to go to China by the Board of the Yale-in-China Association, which sponsored a middle school for boys and a teaching hospital in Changsha, Hunan. DR served as director of religious education and counseling while WR taught music.
1933 Daughter Betty Jean born
1935 Rugh family returned to New Haven where DR received a Ph.D. in religious education from Yale
1936 Rugh family returned to China, with a stop in Hawaii, where DR was ordained as a Congregational minister
1936-1944 DR served as Mission Representative of Yale-in-China initially in Changsha and later in Yuanling, where the Yale-in-China school and hospital were evacuated to avoid Japanese troops entering Changsha.
1944 Rugh family returned to the U.S.
1945-1949 After the war was over DR returned to China to resettle the Yale-in-China school and hospital in Changsha. WR and BJR joined him in 1946, BJR attending Shanghai American School 1947-1949 until evacuated when the Communists entered Shanghai. WR and BJR returned to the U.S.
1949-1951 DR remained in Changsha after the Communist army arrived. As the months passed it became more difficult for him to associate with his friends and to help with the affairs of the school. He was isolated in two rooms of his home and spent time playing his cello, writing poetry, reading, and writing long, frequent letters to WR and BJR. DR was under surveillance and subject to frequent questioning, with demands that he confess to being an American spy. In 1951 the school gymnasium, which was being rebuilt with Yale-in-China funds, was completed and shortly after DR was put on trial and sentenced to be deported. He was taken to Canton and put in prison but after a few days was brought to the border where he could walk to Hong Kong.
1952 Following a year of rest in the U.S. DR becamse Dean of Men at the College of Idaho
1954 DR accepted position as Assistant Director for the Federal Point Four Aid program to Israel and DR and WR lived in Israel
1956-1964 DR and WR went to Taiwan where DR was International Secretary for the YMCA in Taipei
1964 The Rughs went to California to retire but later in the year joined VISTA, going to Norfolk, Virginia where WR trained teachers for the Headstart program and DR trained community workers.
1966 Afer another brief period of retirement the Rughs rejoined VISTA and lived at Mammoth Cave National Park where they taught inner city youth in the Job Corps
1970 DR and WR moved to Bristol Village to live nearer Betty Jean, who was now married to David Elder. They continued their educational work in various capacities.
1981 DR died
Scope and Contents
These papers provide valuable insight on the work of Dwight and Winifred Rugh with the Yale-in-China Association in Hunan province from 1931 to 1951. Frequent detailed letters to family and friends document the upheaval experienced due to the Sino-Japanese War and Communist takeover.
The Rugh Family Papers complement the archives of the Yale-China Association that are held at Yale's Sterling Memorial Library Manuscripts and Archives. Dwight Rugh's official staff correspondence and various motion picture films taken by Rugh are in the Yale-China Association Records. The Rugh Family Papers provide perspective on the family and personal life of the Rughs but also describe their daily work in Changsha and Yuanling. Letters of Betty Jean Rugh from her time at Shanghai American School complement the Shanghai American School archives found in Yale Divinity School Library Record Group no. 132.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1924-1953
II. Writings, 1921-1980
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1948-2000
Missions -- China; Communism -- China; Rugh, D. DeK. (Dwight DeKalb); Rugh, Winifred; Yale-China Association; Yali Middle School; Shanghai American School
- Correspondence, 1924-1953; Series I
  - To extended family in U.S.
    Scope and Contents
    These letters are written by Dwight and Winifred Rugh primarily to "Dear Ones", to Dwight's sister Winifred and her husband Elgin, to "Father", "Aunt May and Gordon"
    - Dwight (DR) and Winifred (WR) studying at North China Language School in Peiping [Beijing]; descriptions of daily life and activities; First Peoples' Convention of the Republic of China held in Beijing, 1930 Nov - 1931 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Move to Shanghai; preparations for and move to Changsha; teaching at Yali Middle School, 1931 Jun - 1932 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Incl. re. visit of Chiang Kai Shek to Yali campus; political conditions disruptive, 1932 Nov - 1933 Feb (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Betty Jean (BJR) Rugh born March 12, 1933; family goes to Kuling for summer; 309 students at school, 1933 Mar-1934 Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
      WR and BJR visited California during this period, due to the death of Winifred's father, then returned to China. There is a gap in letters home while the Rughs were in New Haven, CT on furlough 1935-1936, where Dwight earned a Ph.D. from Yale.
    - Return to China following furlough with stop in Honolulu where DR was ordained; to Kuling during summer; Japan attacks on China lead to evacuations of missionaries, 1936 Sep - 1937 Sep (Box 1, Folder 5)
      The Rughs were evacuated to Honolulu; DR returned to China in July 1937 while WR and BJR went to California where WR attended university. Yali Middle School moved to Yuanling. Upon return to China in 1940, WR and BJR went to Shanghai American School where WR taught and then to Yuanling in December 1940.
    - At Yuanling and summer house in Shih Ch'iao; DR and WR teaching at Yali Middle School, 1941 Jul - 1943 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Family in New Haven for furlough then DR returned to China and WR and BJR first to California and then China, 1945 Mar - 1946 Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Summer at Nan Yo then return to Changsha; WR and BJR to Shanghai American School; DR treasurer of International Hunan Relief Committee, 1947 Apr - Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - DR to Hong Kong on business; WR evacuated to Shanghai, where she taught kindergarten at Shanghai American School, 1948 Feb-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - WR back in Changsha; soldiers around, uneasy feeling; WR and BJR return to US in 1949; DR remains in Changsha, 1949 Jan - 1950 Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - DR alone in Changsha, 1951 Feb-May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - To friends, the Smith sisters, in U.S.
    These letters were written by Winifred Rugh to Ruth and Edith Smith of North Haven, CT, who are addressed as "Dear Two" or "Dear Ones"
    - Incl. re. journey to China; stop in Honolulu; daily life at North China Language School in Beijing, 1930 Jan-Nov (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Daily life at language school; visit to the Great Wall; move to Changsha, 1931 Jan - Oct (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Flood refugees crowding Changsha; plans to go on furlough to New Haven; return to China, 1932 Jan - 1936 Sep (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Summer in Kuling; disruption from Sino-Japanese war; move to Honolulu; DR returns to China; WR and BJR to California, then return to Shanghai in July 1939, 1937 Apr-1939 Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Trip to Yuanling; teaching activities; bombings in nearby cities, 1940 Nov- 1944 Jan (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Family in California; DR returns to Shanghai first and then WR and BJR return and are at Shanghai American School, 1945 Sep - 1948 Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dwight Rugh to Winifred Rugh
    These letters were written by Dwight to his wife when they were separated; some are addressed to both Winifred and Betty Jean. Dwight and Winifred referred to themselves as "De" and "Fe".
    - DR to WR from Honolulu before marriage; while WR is in California at the time of her father's death, while WR and BJR are in Kuling, 1924 May - 1937 Jun (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - DR in Honolulu, returns to China; at Yuanling with BJR; visits to Shih Ch'iao; WR in Changsha, 1938 Jul - 1943 Aug (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - DR returning to China after time in California; at Shanghai YMCA; student strikes in Kunming aea; arranging to buy surplus Army materials for mission, 1945 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - DR in Shanghai; tells of Jewish refugees from several European countries; gathering supplies for Changsha; long arduous trip to Changsha, 1946 Jan-Mar (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - DR in Changsha; much rebuilding necessary; involved with Hunan International Relief Committee; teaching, 1946 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Planning for WR and BJR's return to Changsha, 1946 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - WR and BJR evacuated to Shanghai; DR remains in Changsha; school continues, 1948 Nov (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Daily letters from DR in Changsha, 1948 Dec (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - DR in Changsha; encourages WR to return, 1949 Jan (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - WR and BJR return to California; Communists occupy Shanghai, 1949 Mar (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - DR in Changsha; Yali continues classes; DR working on financial accounts, 1949 Jun (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - DR tours flooded areas in Hunan; Communist forces near Changsha; work with Hunan Foundation for Rural Reconstruction, 1949 Jul (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Communists enter Changsha; school resumes with no restrictions, 1949 Aug-Oct (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Daily life in Changsha, 1949 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Daily life in Changsha; discussing possible changes to Yali education, 1950 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Daily life in Changsha; still no progress in DR's application to leave Changsha, 1950 May (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Daily life in Changsha; response to WR letters, 1950 Jun-Jul (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Daily life in Changsha; responses to WR letters, 1950 Aug (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Daily life in Changsha; friends leaving, 1950 Sep-Oct (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - 44th anniversary of Yale-in-China; DR given permission to leave China; inspection of baggage raised questions; falsely charged re. some items; departure delayed., 1950 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Daily life in Changsha; responses to WR letters, 1951 Jan (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Daily life in Changsha; responses to WR letters; BJR considering colleges, 1951 Feb (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Daily life in Changsha; all missionaries leaving, 1951 Mar (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Daily life in Changsha; several letters contain poems by DR, 1951 Apr (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - DR finally allowed to leave Changsha; returns to California, 1951 May (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Winifred Rugh to Dwight Rugh
    These letters were written by Winifred to her husband when they were separated
    - WR in Changsha for dental work; DR in Yuanling, 1943 Jul-Aug (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - WR and BRJ in California where WR was teaching school; DR in Changsha, 1949 Jun - 1950 Dec (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Betty Jean Rugh to her parents
    - DR in China; BJR and WR in California; letters re. school and daily activities, 1945 Nov - 1946 Jul (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - BJR at Shanghai American School; school activities described, 1947 Jan-Nov (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - BJR at Shanghai American School; school activities described, 1948 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - BJR evacuated from Shanghai in May; goes to Hong Kong, then to California in July, 1949 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - BJR in California, 1950 Feb-Oct (Box 3, Folder 49a)
    - BJR adjusting to life in U.S.; high school activities; begins studies at Oberlin College, 1951 Mar-Oct (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - BJR at Oberlin College, 1952 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - BJR at Oberlin College, 1952 May-Dec (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - BJR at Oberlin College, 1953 Jan-Nov (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Betty Jean Rugh from her parents
    - DR returning to China; in Shanghai, 1945 Nov - 1946 Apr (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - DR in Changsha; BJR at Shanghai American School, 1946 May-1947 Dec (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - DR and WR in Changsha; BJR at Shanghai American School, 1948 Jan-JUn (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - DR and WR in Changsha; BJR at Shanghai American School, 1948 Sep-Dec (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - DR and WR in Changsha; advice in case of evacuation; BJR goes to Hong Kong, 1949 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - BJR and WR in California; DR in Changsha, 1949 May-Dec (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - DR in Changsha; letters include poems, 1950 Mar-Dec (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - DR in Changsha; fatherly advice, 1951 Mar-Apr (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - DR in Changsha - advice to BJR re. college choice; DR returns to U.S.; BJR at Oberlin, 1951 May-Oct (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - DR tells of his job search; takes job at College of Idaho, 1952 Jan-Dec (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - DR in Idaho, 1953 Jan-Oct (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Letters of others
    - Incl. from E. Fay Campbell, Executive Secretary of Yale-in-China to families of staff in Changsha (1931); from Thomas Gibb, Principal of Shanghai American School re. school work of BJR (1947); to WR from students at Yali Middle School (1948); excerpt of letters from Arthur Rugh, uncle of DR (n.d.); Kenneth Scott Latourette to WR re. delay in DR getting exit permit from Changsha (1950), 1931-1951, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 65)
- Writings, 1921-1980; Series II
  - Poems by DR, 1921-1980 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - DR journals of travel from U.S. to Changsha (1936); life in Changsha (1938), 1936-1938 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Essay on "Democracy" (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - DR notes for 4 session presentation on "Principles of Christian Leadership" for C.E. Conference, Kokoshi, 1938 Apr (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Compositions by BJR, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 69)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1948-2000; Series III
  - Excerpt from minutes of Yale-in-China Association Meeting of the Trustees of June 17, 1945 re. terms for reappointment of DR, 1948 Dec 27 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Newspapers clippings re. BJR scholarship to Oberlin College, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Program of memorial service for Dwight Rugh with biographical sketch, 1981 Mar 29 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Commentary by Betty Jean Rugh Elder on Yale-China History chapter, with biographical information about parents, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Family Bibles belonging to Charles E. Rugh (father of DR), to DR, WR and BJR (see notes in box) (Box 4)